Hello class, this is the
question review for angina.
So we have a 59-year-old
male with a history of
type 2 diabetes presenting
to the physician with a
squeezing pain in his chest
during his daily runs.
The pain is relieved
by rest and he has
prescribed the drug which
quickly terminates the
episode by inducing a
decrease in preload.
Which does this describe?
So looking at the
presentation, since this
pain is relieved by rest,
we know that this is a
stable angina episode.
Because, again,
that's called angina
of exertion or angina of work.
And really the top
drugs would be nitrates,
beta blockers, or a calcium
channel blocker. And
remember, that's usually
the standard of care
except for vasospastic
angina, which we don't use
beta blockers because
you can get the unopposed
alpha effect just like
you would with cocaine.
The other thing we know
is that the drug stops
the pain quickly and also
induces a decrease in
the preload. so looking
at the choices we do have
aspirin and although
aspirin is sometimes taken
at the first sign of an mi
it would not help with the
pain when we're thinking
about aspirin and its effects
and how it's in a reversible
cycle oxygenase inhibitor
by doing that it does
prevent the production of
thromboxane, which is responsible
for platelet aggregation,
but it would not have
an effect on preload.
Diltiazim is a calcium
channel blocker, and it
does make sense that it
can be used for angina.
Diltiazim can also lower
the action in the
pacemaker and in
the AV node. But
it doesn't decrease
preload. If anything, it
decreases afterload due
to the fact that it is
an arterial vasodilator.
And diltiazem would
not work quickly.
Metoprolol is the
selective beta-1 adrenergic
antagonists. And
again, by blocking
norepinephrine at the beta
-1 receptor, you're going
to decrease cardiac
output and heart rate.
And that does help,
but it doesn't
have an effect on
the venous return.
The one that has
the effect on the
venous return are
going to be specific
venodilators. And the one
that makes sense here is
going to be nitroglycerin.
And not only does a decreased
preload, it's going to work
quickly because remember,
with nitroglycerin, you're
going to put it under
the tongue because it gets
quickly into the venous
circulation because the
sublingual route avoids the
first pass effect. And
remember that with patients
taking nitroglycerin, if you
do have the situation where
the patient has taken maybe
two tablets and doesn't
get relief from chest pain,
they probably should go
to the hospital because
it could be perhaps an MI.
And then ranolazine, I will
say, is a medication that's
used for chronic angina.
It's going to block the late
sodium channels. So by
less sodium coming into the
myocyte, you're also getting
less of a calcium inside.
Calcium is responsible
for the contractility.
One thing about ranolazine
is that it's subjected
to SIP inhibition. So
something like grapefruit
juice can increase the levels.
Same thing with calcium
channel blockers. But
ranolazine does exhibit
potassium channel blockade.
We call delayed
repolarization and
that can increase
the QT interval. So
that is reserved
for chronic angina.
And then remember, the
chest pain comes from this
decrease in oxygen supply
demand. There's an imbalance.
So decrease blood flow
and then increase in
oxygen consumption. And
the pathophys behind
that has to do with the
fact that the The heart
rate is elevated, as
is the contractility.
So beta blockers do a
good job to reverse that.
Afterload is high, and that
contributes to high
oxygen consumption.
So what will be
needed to reduce the
afterload is an
arterial basal dilator,
like tiltiazem or
maybe amlodipine. And
then the preload being
elevated and also
contributing to an
increase in oxygen
consumption has to do
with high venous return.
So giving something like a
nitrate is going to reduce
the venous return. And that
makes sense. Less blood
going back, the less work the
heart has to do to pump it
out. and then also understand
when there is a degree
of anaerobic metabolism
you're going to shift the
glycolysis pathway towards
lactate that's number one and
then the accumulation of
substance P is going to sensitize
the nerve endings and that
contributes to the pain
A 62-year-old male
with episodic, typical
angina is managed
with medication.
On the internet, he
obtained a phosphodiesterase
-5 inhibitor to resolve
symptoms of male
impotence. during therapy
for angina he also self
-administered this pde5
inhibitor and experienced
a profound hypotensive
episode which drug was
prescribed so this is
obviously an interaction
between between a nitric
oxide donor and a drug like
sidenafil because when
you take sildenafil you're
inhibiting this enzyme
pde5 and you're enhancing
cyclic gmp which nitric
oxide donors are already
doing so the smooth muscle
relaxation will be pronounced
extreme mesodilation
and as I mentioned when
your blood pressure goes
down severely the way the
body compensates is by
invoking sympathetics and
that will lead to a patient
having perhaps an ischemia
such as an MI and early
on we did have reported
deaths in patients that
were taking the two together
so it's recommended that
there is at least a 48
hour nitrate free interval
between these drugs and
the sildenafil.
So, again, aspirin
would not fit.
This is an antiplatelet drug.
Isosorbide, again, when
we're looking at the
names, you see that it
ends with mononitrate.
So that would be, in
fact, the best choice
here. That is the
nitric oxide donor.
metoprolol is beta 1 selective
and this one again what
I would be most concerned
about is the fact that this
is a av node suppressant
and we'll study this going
forward in anti-arrhythmic
drug lecture that can be a
problem the patient can get
severe bradycardia so you need
to be mindful that they
don't get AB node blockade.
Ticca-Grelor is the direct
acting ADP receptor antagonist.
This is the one
that doesn't need
activation, unlike clopidogrel.
But, number one, it might
be more pricey, first
of all. But secondly,
probably being direct,
you probably have a
greater incidence of bleed
with this one as opposed
to, say, clopidogrel.
And then propanolol is
interesting because it is
going to be the non-selective.
It's beta-1 and beta-2.
So what I would say
with this one is that
if you have an asthmatic
or a COPD patient,
beta-2 blockade in the
lungs are going to cause
the patient to get
constriction and they'll have
difficulty breathing. In
the liver, if you block
beta-2, you're not converting
glycogen to glucose.
If you also block beta-2 in
the vessels, you're going
to get more of a reduced
blood flow. And that can
complicate somebody that has
peripheral vascular disease.
So again, this is an
important drug interaction
that you should be mindful
of and also to understand
the whole concept of reflexive
tachycardia that occurs.
And that's due to
baroreceptor reflex mechanism.
okay so it's all about
increasing cyclic gmp and the
extreme smooth muscle
relaxation is going to cause
hypotension resulting in
reflexive tachycardia due to the
invocation of sympathetics
and remember we have in our
body through the endothelial
cell it's mediated by
sometimes acetylcholine and
then L-arginine through nitric
oxide synthase, it's
doing this naturally. But
nitrates, what they do is
they're donors of nitric oxide.
Not much here to say. We
know about the throbbing
and the vascular headache
and the connection between,
say, nitrates affording
vasodilation and causing
throbbing and then if
you give like a drug like
sumatriptan which is going
to cause vasoconstriction
and help with the
throbbing we understand why
patients can't take many
doses of the triptans because
along with serotonin
syndrome the issue is that
we would worry about
patients having an elevation
in blood pressure and then
of course they may have
an angina episode if they
were prone to ischemia.
I did mention that
increasing cyclic GMP
through nitric oxide
will decrease platelet
activation but we
have no clinical proof
that it can work as
an antiplatelet drug.
So this patient is a 69
-year-old male brought
to the ED with complaints
of a severe headache.
His blood pressure was
found to be 200 over
100, and that's a
very dangerous number.
he has a history of type 2
diabetes which has progressed
to renal disease he has
administered medication
which stabilizes his blood
pressure several hours later
he is confused and he's
red in the face or his skin
and he's given vitamin b12
what's the cause of this
recent presentation So,
which is standout is vitamin
B12, because we know that's
an antidote for something.
The other thing is his
high blood pressure
and the fact that he
has renal disease.
So, we know that
B12 is a possible
antidote for looking
at the choices,
sodium nitroprusside.
and the reason being is
that this has cyanide
as part of its structure
and since he is in
fact having issues with
his kidneys he's
probably not excreting
the cyanide and he's
becoming presenting with
a cyanotic poisoning,
cyanide poisoning
So giving something
like hydroxycobalamin is
going to bind those
cyanide atoms and make
cyanocobalamin, which
is another form of B12.
So, you know, B12, we'll
talk about it a little
bit. This is when people
have missing intrinsic
factor, and that's a
GI problem, and they
can't absorb oral B12,
and they're given a shot,
like cyanocobalamin
or hydroxycobalamin.
In this case, whatever they
don't use for their body
as B12, they will excrete
because Bs, vitamin B and C,
they're water-soluble. So
that's an appropriate one.
Thiosulfate, the sulfate
in that compound combines
with the cyanide and it
also allows for it to be
neutralized and excreted.
But my most recent
experience is that most
hospitals were using the B12.
So nitroprusside,
in fact, is the
best answer for this question.
Aspirin, if we were overdosing
on aspirin, probably
it would be about ventilation
and probably to perform
ion trapping with something
like sodium bicarbonate.
And remember, early on, the
patient has
respiratory alkalosis.
As things start progressing
and there's a change in
the mitochondria, then they
go into metabolic acidosis.
For diltiazem, if there's
an overdose of this group,
calcium channel blockers
in the pancreas, if you're
blocking calcium in, you're
not going to be able to
release insulin. So in an
overdose, patients can in
fact be cardiac unstable
and they may need calcium,
especially if we're
thinking about contraction
of the heart, they
may also need insulin.
Metoprolol, even
though it's not beta
-2 blockade as much
as, say, propanolol,
in an overdose, you
still have to make sure
that the patient doesn't
get hypoglycemia.
And the reason being is
if you're blocking beta-2,
you may not convert your
glycogen to glucose. So
patients, if they overdose
on beta blockers, they may
become hypoglycemic, and
you have to give glucagon.
And then lastly,
ranolazine, you would worry
about the QT interval.
And I'm not going to
confuse that right now, what
medication you would
give, but we'll go through
that a little bit later.
So here the best answer
for this cyanide poisoning,
so to speak, would be
to give B12 and the drug
is sodium nitroprusside.
and the thing about sodium
nitroprusside that makes
it appropriate for a
hypertensive crisis is that it's
not only affecting the preload
but it's also acting as
an arterial vasodilator
and that will decrease the
afterload and that helps
bring down the blood pressure
a 60 year old male has
been well controlled for
hypertension he recently observed
changes in his mouth which
resembled the following
which drug is the most likely
cause so venetoine cyclosporine
and of course calcium
channel blockers there may
be an increase in growth
factors which raise the
production of collagen. So
over time people may present
with this enlarged gum.
So the best answer here
looking at the choices would
be probably philodipine
because that is the calcium
channel blocker and this
is the dihydropyridine.
Atenolol being a beta
-1 adrenergic blocker, I
probably would worry
about AV node suppression,
okay?
Sodium nitroprusside,
we just covered.
Ticlopidine, this is
the one that I said
you'll never prescribe,
but they might ask you
on boards. This is
the first ADP receptor
antagonist, and the
warning was neutropenia,
okay? So, patient has
sore throat, fever,
flu-like symptoms, you
look at their CBC, the
white blood cells are
of cyclobatine goes,
okay? And you
make sure that the
patient is not
prone to infection.
And then tyrofibin is
a glycoprotein 2B, 3A
inhibitor. This would be
in patients that maybe
cannot tolerate ADP
receptor blockers, or
maybe has an aspirin
allergy and can't take
aspirin. This would be
given, it's short-term,
continuous.
It's given as a parenteral,
and that is going to be
used post-stenting. So the
best choice here for this
gingival hyperplasia is
going to be phenyldipine.
So
going back to calcium
channel blockers, this
vascular smooth muscle
cell is the arterial.
Calcium enters the cell,
binds to calmodulin. they
are complex because
calmodulin is its binding
protein myosin light
chain kinase allows for
phosphorylation to happen
you're going to get a
interaction with actin
and that's going to cause
contraction so that would be
now what we would say basal
constriction so by
giving something like
amlodipine, for lodipine,
you actually prevent this
from happening and you're
going to get relaxation.
Again, on the flip side, the
beta-2 agonist, as I mentioned,
that would be this
whole idea of increasing
cyclic AMP and getting
now relaxation because
you're enhancing cyclic
GMP. That would be more
for something like
albuterol. So again, not to
confuse the issue, That's
just a little bit about
a review or a preview
for when you do lung.
Calcium channel blockers,
the dihydropyridines,
specific for the arterial
rolls. They're going
to bring down the peripheral
vascular resistance,
and they're going to
decrease the afterload.
So remember that equation,
BP equals cardiac
output times peripheral
vascular resistance.
Peripheral vascular resistance,
think about arterial
vasodilators like
calcium channel blockers.
The cardiac output, you
think of beta blockers.
The rapamalindiltiazim can
still achieve a similar
effect on the arterial, but
they also decrease the heart
rate because they are
working at the pacemaker and
they're also decreasing
ventricular contractility.
So because of that, they are
also used as antiarrhythmics.
So when we do the classes
of those antiarrhythmics,
class 4 is going to be
rarapamyl and diltiazem.
Class 2 is going to be
the beta blockers. The
other two, again, I
won't confuse you right
now, but that's just a
little bit of a preview.
Calcium channel blocker
adverse effects.
So the edema, the
dizziness, the headache,
mainly because of the
arterial vasodilating
effect. Because
you're increasing RAS,
renin, angiotensin,
aldosterone. Aldosterone
allows the kidney
to sweep up the
sodium in the water
and you get edema.
The headache, because
again in the cerebral
vessels you're
getting vasodilation.
And of course the dizziness.
Tachycardia, mainly with
the dihydropyridines,
bradycardia with the non,
because again, they are also
working in the heart. They're
going to lower your heart
rate, and they're going
to lower the contraction.
Constipation, again,
because if you are blocking
calcium, you're affecting
peristalsis, and
so that kind of slows
down the gut motility.
We talked about ginger
overgrowth, grapefruit
juice interaction.
So if I was using
verapamil and I had
a diet of grapefruit,
I probably would be
prone to bradycardia.
Verapamil increases
digoxin plasma levels.
DIG is an AV node
suppressant and is also used
for improving contractility
in certain cases of
CHF. But it's a narrow
therapeutic index drug.
And rirapamil, by the way
it works, it will prevent
the dioxin from being
excreted in the kidney
because it affects some
of the transporters there.
Management of toxicity,
you could give supportive
care, IV, calcium, and
then insulin. Because as
I said, shifting calcium
into the pancreatic
beta cells allows for
insulin to be released. If
I'm blocking there, then
insulin is not being
released and now the patient
becomes hyperglycemic.
A 19-year-old male was
brought to the ED having
consumed a bottle of his
grandmother's medication in a
suicide attempt. On exam,
his heart rate is 45 beats
per minute, with a blood
pressure of 90 over 60.
He has difficulty breathing.
An EKG showed sinus
bradycardia and the
presence of a first
-degree AV block.
in the labs his glucose is
55 what did he overdose on
so this this cannot be any
more clearer because you
have it all pretty much
there you're having the
hypoglycemia you're having
low BP the heart rate is 80 is
45 and the AV block is
present so this has to be a
situation where the patient
consumed a beta blocker and
the fact that he's having
difficulty breathing probably
shows that it can be beta
1 but most likely it's
non-selective beta 1 and
beta 2 and that's definitely
confirming that with the
glucose of 55 because that's
really dependent than on
beta-2 block in the liver.
So looking at this,
abcixumab, if anything,
that would cause
bleeding because
it's a glycoprotein
2B3A inhibitor.
Fulodipine is an
arterial vasodilator
that is calcium
channel blocker.
Nitroglycerin sublingual
would not cause an AB block
and a low heart rate. If
anything, being that it's
vasodilating, it should
cause reflexive tachycardia.
It shouldn't have any
problems with breathing with
the nitro, and it would
not affect the glucose.
So, perpanolol or verapamil?
While I could say that
verapamil in an overdose can,
in fact, cause both of
these, if anything verapamil
would not cause the
glucose to be 55 it would
probably be much higher and
verapamil would not affect
the breathing as a matter
of fact if you cannot
tolerate a beta blocker
and you need something with
a synergistic type mechanism
you can give verapamil
to like say an asthmatic
or COPD patient so the
best answer is going to be
propanolol okay and what's
concerning here is basically
everything, but the
AV block is what we would
expect and we need to be
mindful of. So when prescribing
this medication, you
definitely need to call
the patient back and check
their heart rate and blood
pressure consistently.
And so then with beta blockers
in the SA node, you're
blocking the pacemaker.
So you're getting a
decrease in oxygen demand
and heart rate. In the
myocardium, you're getting
a decrease in contractility.
In the arterial oils,
same thing with decreasing
the oxygen demand, you may
have some decrease in
afterload. okay and the the
one thing to know is again
start matching up the receptors
to the medication so even
though we know it's a
beta blocker it's going to
block the beta one receptors
in the heart for norepinephrine
the receptor physiology
is going to be g-stimulatory
so you're increasing
adenyl cyclase increasing
cyclic AMP you're increasing
protein kinase a and
increasing and calcium in is
going to cause contraction.
So it would make sense
that if you give a blocker,
it would be the opposite.
Okay, so again, probably,
and I don't want
to, you know, go over
this too much because
it's going to come up
again in almost all of
the lectures that I'm
doing for this block.
AV node block is
important, but for
this particular
lecture for angina,
Prince metal, vasospastic,
you don't give a beta
blocker. Because again,
the similarity between
this and the fact that
we don't want to give a
beta blocker to somebody
that's overdosing on
cocaine. Usually we would
give something like libetolol
or you can give something
like phantolamine.
The other thing to know is the
intrinsic sympathetic
mimetic effect.
these two,
pindylol and acebutylol
pindylol is non-selective
acebutylol is selective
so it's beta 1 that would
be nice but the fact
that it is increasing
sympathetic action which
would mean that it's
increasing the workload of
the heart and that would
be a problem if somebody
had some type of ischemia
like angina or post-MI
so this is a 59 year old
and he is brought to the
ed because of chest pain
that started 45 minutes
ago and is not relieved
by nitro he has a history
of hyperlipidemia and
asthma his ecg reveals an
st segment depression
and leads v2 to v3 he
started on a medication
that may cause a mixed Next,
respiratory alkalosis
and metabolic
acidosis if taken in excess.
What's the mechanism?
So this guy is
definitely having an MI.
And, you know, aside
from the chest pain, the
nitroglycerin didn't
do anything. And they
see ST segment depressions
in lead V2 to V3.
So probably in looking
at this, the alkalosis
followed by the acidosis,
he was probably given
an aspirin. And that
is usually appropriate.
They say at the first sign,
even as EMS is coming,
they would give you, as part
of the therapy, aspirin.
So, looking at the choices,
blockade of the ADP
receptor, that's
going to be mostly
something like
clopidogrel, or
praseguel, or ticagrelor.
Blockade of the L-type
calcium channel, that
could be verapamil, or
the dihydropyridine drugs.
Inhibition of glycoprotein
2B3A That is maybe if he
was being stented And it could
be that he will But that's
going to be something like
Ephibitide or tyrofibane
Phosphodiesterase 3 That's
going to be something
like Silostasol or
diapritamol And we tend to
give that in patients
That have intermittent
cortication Those patients
They get tired walking
because they have
atherosclerosis in their legs
and that has to do with
a reduced blood flow.
So giving something
like that enhances
prostacyclin which
keeps things flowing.
So that's not the case here.
Irreversible phosphodiesterase
5 inhibition, that's
going to be something like
sildenafil. Again, in this
lecture, we made the point
that giving those drugs with
nitrates can lead to extreme
hypotension and that can
lead to invoked sympathetics
and myocardial infarction.
And then we know that
this is the right answer.
Irreversible inhibition
of psychooxygenase. That
definitely applies to aspirin.
And remember, with aspirin,
it is a salicylate. So
some of the things that we
need to be mindful of with
salicylates, as an aside, is
those patients that are
considered to be pediatric,
because that can
cause Rye syndrome.
The other thing to know
is that aspirin therapy,
if we're thinking about
patients that don't really
need it for primary use,
they may open themselves
up to GI effects because
you're blocking the
***-1 enzyme especially,
and that is going to
cut your prostaglandins in
your GI tract. So you're
losing your cytoprotective
mechanism, and that's
going to create stomach
discomfort. And in
worst case scenario, you're
going to get GI bleed.
So as I mentioned, if
you had had an MRI, a
stroke, which is called
secondary cardiovascular
disease, you will
be put on aspirin.
primary again that needs
to be evaluated by the
physician they'll do an ac
svd score they'll calculate
if you're diabetic if
you're a smoker your age
your your gender and if
they believe that you need
aspirin therapy they'll tell
you as I said in the past
this wasn't done and
patients that were young
were just self-medicating
on aspirin and the incidence
of people that they saw
presenting with GI bleed
was high so this is why
they they changed the
guidelines okay and that
goes for everything always
consider the individual
patient what's their clinical
history what other
comorbidities they have how old
they are again again if
you had a patient that
maybe was older and you
were worrying about them
possibly having an MI or
stroke and they had had
GI bleed in the past,
it's okay to think about
antiplatelet therapy, but
maybe you wouldn't give
aspirin. Maybe you would
give corpidogrel. The other
thing to note is that the
metabolic acidosis, it
all has to do biochemically
with the uncoupling
of oxidative phosphorylation
in the mitochondria.
And lastly, with the
ADP receptor blockers,
Cyclopidine, I can't
say it enough, that's
the one that can
induce neutropenia.
All of them are pro-drugs,
they need to be activated.
Tikalgralor doesn't, and
neither does Kanggralor,
and Kanggralor is newer,
it's IV, most likely
going to be at a facility
that does stenting.
Clopidogrel is very popular
but being a pro-drug
it needs to be activated
by 2C19. There are people
that have mutations in
their SIP or drugs that
can inhibit SIP 2C19 and
that is omeprazole. That's
a very popular proton
pump inhibitor that we use
for the GI, for GERD,
for peptic ulcer disease.
If you're taking omeprazole
with clopidogrel, chances
are you're not going to get
any antiplatelet action.
So the idea here is
either you change the PPI
or you change your ADP
receptor antagonist.
As a class, all of
these drugs will cause
bleeding. Patients should
be mindful of that.
Okay, again, tyclopidine
and the neutropenia.
And then with the
G2B3A inhibitors, as I
mentioned, these are
given in patients that
have ACS or they have
had a PCI and they
are probably at a
greater risk of thrombus.
They can't tolerate an ADP
receptor blocker or they
have an aspirin allergy.
these will definitely cause
bleeding and then glansman
disease that's the
pathology correlate people
with this have a defective
gp2b3a and what that would
mean is that these patients
are at a higher risk of
bleed and it makes sense
because these drugs that are
inhibitors can cause bleed
okay and so remember with
stenting it's usually
six to twelve months of two
usually it's aspirin and
clopidogrel most people
will tolerate um the two
together sometimes a physician
may say you know have
them take something for
um GERD maybe they'll take
some famotidine. I've seen
that happen several times.
And again, 6 to 12 months.
Some doctors may even say
a little longer. Again,
that depends on the patient.
So again, there's
guidelines, but we also
have to consider the
patient as an individual.
Thank you for your attention.
If there are any
other questions,
please feel free
to reach out. Until
then, I will see
you soon. Thank you.